Okay, so for the exercise,
we're actually going to be using
one of my new favorite APIs called JSON Placeholder.
If you haven't heard about it, it's pretty great.
Because what it does is it basically provides
a bunch of static data that
requires no authentication key or anything.
What it allows you to do is it has
a bunch of different datasets
that allow you to relate between them.
So basically, we'll see here,
we take a look at users, for example.
Users has an ID,
it has all this data ready for you.
But then, if you take a look at something like to-dos,
you'll notice that it even has user ID
and it relates back to those users.
So what you basically have is,
rather than having a dynamic database that oftentimes goes,
like either un-maintained or eventually goes out of service,
this is really just a bunch of static JSON,
but we get to request it as if it were from the backend.
So this is the API that I recommend you all use
going forward when it comes to our exercises.
So for our exercise,
you're going to be using the SailorView app,
and this time your product manager has come to you and says,
we need a user page component.
So we're going to give you some practice as far as basically,
go ahead and create that user page inside of the component folder,
and then inside of that component,
go ahead and use that created lifecycle to go ahead and fetch
all the users from that JSON placeholder API using what we just showed you.
Then go ahead and render that however you see fit,
and then go ahead and make sure you update app.view so that,
if you want to use that dynamic component,
that actually swaps it out correctly when you're using the navigation.
Welcome back everybody. How is the exercise?
All right. Yeah, it looks like people were successful.
So no worries.
In case you find that a little bit complicated,
we're going to walk through the solution right now.
So let's go ahead and do this.
So let me close that, bring that over here.
Actually, you know what I do?
I do want this as a reference.
I'm going to bring this as a new tab.
Okay. All right.
So I'm going to go ahead and I'm going to work in the Say Love You.
Remember that if you are working in your TV forum app,
you can go ahead and use whatever I'm doing in Say Love You as
like an example for how the solution should look in your app.
Okay. So I'm going to go ahead and check out the O9 branch solution.
So that's where this will live.
Okay. So first thing first, what do we want to do?
We want to create a user page.
All right. So what we're going to do inside of our components
folder, user page dot view.
And then I'm going to go ahead and let's set up the script block
and let's set up the style block.
And so taking a look at what we have here,
we have some basic styles.
And so for now, I'm just going to kind of keep it straightforward
in the sense that like, let's just go ahead and pull what we
already have.
So I'm going to actually grab, I think,
the login page is fine for me.
So I'm going to go ahead and actually know it.
Let's see, do-do-do-do, yeah, I'll just grab the login page.
So I'll grab the login page, copy it over into our user page for now.
And I'm going to actually delete these or I'll leave them
because there will actually be a great discussion point for later.
And for now, we'll just call this users,
we'll delete this stuff and we'll just save.
So now if we go back, we are on the home page.
We won't be able to see this yet.
Why?
Because we actually need to update our app.view
so that we actually show that page.
And so for now, we're just going to make it easy
and we're just going to say, OK, well, by default,
we're just going to show the user page.
But we want to show the user page, what do we got to do?
We got to import it because we're actually
going to call that component.
So that way we call it, we register it,
that way it can actually be called later on.
So we save that and refresh, nothing's working, why is that?
Well, we need local dev running.
Let me close that one.
Great, here we go.
OK, so we have our user page up and running, looking good.
And so what do we want to do?
We want to go ahead and fetch our users from this API right here.
So following our best practices, we'll
do the export default object.
And inside of our created, we're actually
going to go ahead and run a function.
What we want to run, ideally, we want something
like this.fetch users.
But we haven't written that, so let's go ahead and write that.
So we'll create a methods here.
And the methods option will contain fetch users.
Inside of here, this is where we're
going to go ahead and run our request.
So we might have a this.userList equals what?
We're going to fetch this API.
And then we're going to take that response.
And then we're going to JSONify by running response.json.
Now again, this is an asynchronous request.
So we need the await keyword.
And we need to tell it that it's async.
Not quite done yet though, because why?
We have this this.userList.
It hasn't been created yet.
This is our reactive data.
So we can go and go ahead and create that.
And so we have our user list.
And that will be an array.
And then we can save.
All right, everything formats.
It looks good.
The code editor is not yelling at us anymore.
And so we aren't seeing anything yet.
And that's totally fine, because why?
We haven't actually rendered it to the screen.
So user list, there we go.
We saved, and we refreshed.
OK, now that we do it, great.
We can actually see all our users here.
But we're going to go ahead and pretty that up a little bit,
because that is pretty hard to read.
So I'm just going to do an unordered list.
And for every one of these users, so user in user list,
we're going to make sure, because we're using a v4 loop,
we're going to assign it a unique key.
And that key can be just be the ID, actually,
that we have up here.
So I'm going to say, do, do.
I'm going to use the ES6 templating, though,
to say user.id.
And the reason for this is because this data set
is on the simpler side, as far as keeping the IDs just numbers.
And so I do know in advance that there
will be other elements that also have very simplistic IDs.
And so prevent that from colliding,
because when it does, view will tell you inside of the console
log, hey, by the way, I'm seeing duplicate keys for elements.
And that will create all sorts of havoc for you.
So try to keep them unique whenever you can.
Again, normally, these will be UU IDs,
and you don't have to worry about it.
And then we can basically render out the user.name.
And then let's go ahead and just then let's just
do what would be fun to do.
Let's do their website, then.
And then we have user.website, save.
There we go.
And we can see now, if we refresh.
OK, we got a lot going on.
Now, for a second here, I panicked, because I was like,
why are we seeing double?
The reason we're seeing double is because we
have the pre-element still there.
So we save that now and refresh.
There you go, much better.
And now we have all our users being rendered on the page.
And is there a way with the dev tools
to see the unique IDs of those items?
Yeah, that's a great question.
So if we take a look at what the context here is,
is that this dynamic key that we're assigning, in this case,
user-1 and so forth, the question here
is around the idea if there is any way to expose that.
And so honestly, off the top of my head,
we can see here that if we're looking at the browser DevTools,
there's nothing actually indicating what the keys are.
And if we take a look at ViewDevTools,
we can see here that one nice thing about DevTools
is that it makes it very clear how you can expose
the different properties of it.
But it does look like, at first glance,
there's nothing obvious kind of indicating
its individual keys.
Like, we can inspect the elements in here
and all the data in here, so in case you ever
debugging anything.
And what's a nice little bonus about this, too, actually,
is that the DevTools allow you to modify it directly.
So if we come in here and just call like Selena
as a middle name, you'll see that it'll actually
update it directly.
So it allows for a kind of a quicker feedback loop
in case you're wondering if your data set is doing something
specific with your code, you can just play around with it
right there rather than call it going back to your component
and faking the data set.
The DevTools allows you to kind of do that in a centralized way.
I wonder, can I do key equals render page like that?
Oh, OK.
Great, so we did discover this at the bare minimum
through this exercise.
If you provide keys to your components,
these are showing up in your DevTools.
So there's something to be said where
if you're at the point where you're probably debugging keys,
at least for your components, it probably is helpful to,
I mean, to be honest, if we're thinking
about like a real world scenario,
the user page would be displaying probably
a user card component.
And then those should show those.
And so for the sake of actually demoing that,
because this is actually something that does occur in apps,
let's do a user card real quick.
And then I'm just going to go ahead and drop that.
We're going to drop this ally.
We're going to keep it simple.
We're just going to assume all user cards are always
list elements.
And then I'm not going to worry about that piece.
And then we're going to go ahead and quickly just define a prop,
default props, and they'll get a user type of object.
And required is true.
Save.
And then inside of user page now,
we can actually import said user card.
And then there we go.
Just use the autocomplete for that.
And then the components.
There we go.
And then again, dropping user card in here.
And then we can then say user card
is what we're going to use here.
We're going to not worry about that.
And then we're just going to make sure we pass user
inside of here.
Like that.
That should self-close, save, OK.
That should do the trick.
It looks like everything's working.
And to validate this real quick, what we're going to do
is we're going to add a quick CSS class called user card.
And I'm just going to say user card has order 2px solid.
Let's just keep it simple.
Let's just do like a black.
And then just like a padding of 10 pixels.
There we go.
OK.
So our cards are rendering.
We have our user page here rendering our list of cards,
which looks good.
And now, if we go ahead and now open the DevTools,
we should see, which I think I saw a glimpse of that
a second ago.
There we go.
The keys are showing up in this case.
So it does look like if you want to inspect the DOM element one,
that remains to be a little bit elusive.
But that said, still a worthy question
worth investigating into.
On the topic of keys, are those keys,
do they need to be unique on a globally all items rendered
on page, or is it kind of scoped to the component?
So if your component renders one list,
is it safe to just use key 1, 2, 3, 4?
Yep.
Oh, sorry.
The yelp was acknowledging the question.
OK.
So the question here is around the scoping of keys,
because we talked about scoping of data.
Data is scoped to the components,
and we have to be very explicit about how it's shared.
Keys, however, are different, because it
has to do with whatever's on the page.
So there's no scoping in regards to keys.
And this is very important, in particular when
it comes to animation and transitions,
is because if you want View to start managing some
of those pieces, those keys do really need to be unique.
Otherwise, you'll start seeing weird glitches of View
trying to calculate how to move things around,
and two or three things at once.
And so yeah, I would treat keys as a universal thing.
This is why knowing the data set that I have,
let me close this.
Knowing the data set that I have,
that is why I prefixed it with user,
so that later we can have photos or comments
or whatever we decide to extend upon.
So good question, though.
Cool.
So we have the ability to go back here to home and log in,
but we don't have a user link.
So let's actually just make sure we wrap that up properly.
So for now, we're just going to keep it simple here.
You might notice, though, when you're inspecting the nav,
that I'm doing something a little bit hacky.
One is that this is technically an anchor link,
but the anchor link doesn't go anywhere.
It actually goes to the top of the page.
But on the click event, you'll notice
that I'm adding this modifier dot prevent.
If you're not familiar with this, think of it like a form.
Form is the one where I typically show off the prevent.
And so what happens a lot of times
when you have forms on an HTML page?
You want to actually stop the event from submitting
and then do some stuff before you submit it.
And so typically, what do you have to do?
If you had a submit form that was like submit registration,
inside of your submit registration function,
you'd have to run what?
You'd have to get the event.
You'd have to run event dot prevent default.
Well, View was like, wait, we do this so often.
Why is that code polluting really logic that's
separate from it?
That's really just basically a logistical implementation.
So by adding dot prevent to your submit,
it automatically basically executes
on that prevent default event so that your code can be cleaner
and you don't have to worry about.
Basically, it's easier to modularize things.
Because otherwise, your functions
have always this context of being attached to an event, which
might not always be true.
So this is a kind of something tactic sugar
that's useful, that's being used.
And so in this case, I'm using click.prevent
to prevent it from actually doing the navigation.
Again, to be very clear, this is hacky,
because we are going to get into official routing
and so we can change URLs and those sort of things.
But for the sake of practice right now,
this is why we have it.
All right, that said, we have an hrf.
Again, following just the same model, click.prevent.
And this time, we're going to show user page.
User, that looks good.
And then here, show user page.
This.currentPage equals user.
OK, OK, that looks good.